Guide to the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
1716-2018
RG 295
Yale University Divinity School Library
65
(168 boxes)
This is a collection of the correspondence, diaries, writings and/or other papers and memorabilia related various individuals, including clergy, missionaries, and faculty and graduates of Andover Theological Seminary, Newton Theological Institution, and Andover Newton Theological School faculty members.
Biographical / Historical
The papers in this collection were gathered at Andover Newton Theological Seminary and transferred to the Yale Divinity School Library in 2017 when Andover Newton became affiliated with Yale Divinity School. Andover Newton traces its roots to the early 1800s and the desire to prepare a well-educated clergy among both Congregationalist and Baptists. With the 1778 founding of Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, and the establishment of a separate department of divinity in 1807, the Andover Theological Seminary was created. Instruction at the southern Merrimack River Valley campus continued until 1907, when the trustees decided to move the school to the urban setting of Cambridge, Massachusetts, to broaden the curriculum and establish closer ties with the academic world. In 1908, plans for a formal affiliation with Harvard Divinity School were started, but merger attempts resulted in a legal struggle over adherence to Andover's founding principles.
The move to Cambridge left the school with a dwindling enrollment. In 1931, at the invitation of the Newton Theological Institution, Andover relocated to Newton Centre. In 1965, the two schools formally merged, forming the Andover Newton Theological School.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, diaries, writings and/or other papers and memorabilia of various individuals, including graduates and former faculty members of Andover Theological Seminary, Newton Theological Institution and Andover Newton Theological School, as well as clergy, church leaders and missionaries. The papers of these men and women have been placed in the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers record group because the quantity or substance of the material did not warrant a separate record group.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically by the names of the individuals.
Andros, Thomas, 1759-1845; Anderson, Frederick L. (Frederick Lincoln), 1862-1938; Anthony, Alfred Williams, 1860-1939; Bailey, Albert Edward, 1871-1951; Barrows, Homer, 1806-1881; Bartlett, Ernest Merrill, 1870-1905; Berkeley, James P. (James Percival), 1879-1971; Bigelow, Asahel, 1797-1877; Boardman, George Dana, 1828-1903; Boynton, Grace Morrison, 1890-1970; Boynton, Nehemiah, 1856-1933; Brown, Charles Rufus, 1849-1914; Calkins, Wolcott, 1831-1924; Carpenter, C.H., 1835-1887; Cochrane, Wilbur Willis; Dabney, Vaughan, 1888-1973; Davis, Jacob, 1812-1903; Denison, Frederic, 1819-1901; Dodge, William B., 1783-1869; Donovan, Winfred; Dunbar, Robert Wayland; Emmons, Nathanael, 1745-1840; Eaton, W. H. (William Harrison), 1841-1908; Fackre, Gabriel, 1926-2018; Fisher, Abial, 1787-1862; Gilkey, James Gordon, 1889-1964; Gulliver, John Putnam, 1819-1894; Hall, Robert Beals, 1845-1876; Fiske, Daniel Taggert, 1819-1903; Handspicker, M. B. (Meredith Brook), 1932-; Hazelton, Roger, 1909-1988; Hopkins, Samuel, 1721-1803; Horr, George Edwin, 1856-1927; Hovey, Augusta; Hovey, George Rice, 1860-1943; Ives, Hilda Libby, 1886-1969; Judson, Adoniram, 1788-1850; Kimball, James, 1789-1821; King, Henry Melville; Labaree, Benjamin Woods, 1865-1904; Lamson, William, 1812-1882; Leverett, Warren, 1805-1872; Leverett, Washington, 1805-1889; Lindsay, Samuel Macaulay, 1886-; Loesch, Russell, 1907-1989; Marshall, Harry Ignatius, 1878-; Millard, William Harold, 1877-1909; Millett, Joshua, 1803-1848; Mitchell, Hinckley G. T. (Hinckley Gilbert Thomas), 1846-1920; Morrow, Honoré, 1880-1940; Morton, Margaret M., 1898-; Niijima, Jō, 1843-1890; Nowlan, Ivan S.; Noyes, Charles L.; Page, Frederick Harlan, 1860-1951; Pearson, Eliphalet, 1752-1826; Peck, George Willis, 1931-1990; Pendleton, Othniel A., 1911-; Pepper, George D. B. (George Dana Boardman), 1833-1913; Phillips, Samuel, 1690-1771; Plumb, Albert H. (Albert Hale), 1829-1907; Plumb, Albert Hale, 1863-1961; Price, Hampton Eugene, 1904-1991; Rhees, Rush, 1860-1939; Sanderson, Ross W. (Ross Warren), 1884-; Schauffler, William G. (William Gottlieb), 1798-1883; Smith, Hezekiah, 1737-1805; Smith, Samuel Francis, 1808-1895; Smyth, Egbert Coffin, 1829-1904; Stiles, Abel, 1709-1783; Taylor, Oliver Alden, 1801-1851; West, Stephen, 1735-1819; Wisner, Benjamin B. (Benjamin Blydenburg), 1794-1835; Woods, Leonard, 1774-1854; Woods, Leonard, 1807-1878; White, William James, 1811-1889; Whitman, Benaiah Longley, 1862-1911; Willard, Benjamin, 1783-1862; Winchell, James M. (James Manning), 1791-1820; Edwards, Jonathan, 1745-1801
- Individuals A-L, Series I
  - Anderson, Frederick Lincoln
    Biographical / Historical
    Anderson was born on April 14, 1862 in St. Louis, Missouri. He graduated from the University of Chicago in 1882 and from 1882 to 1885 was Assistant Professor of Latin there. In 1888 he received a B.D. from Baptist Union Theological Seminary, Morgan Park, Illinois and was ordained as a Baptist minister. After serving briefly as Acting Pastor, Second Baptist Church, St. Louis, from 1888 October to 1900 he was Pastor of Second Baptist Church, Rochester, NY. From 1900 to 1933 he was Professor of Biblical Interpretation, Newton Theological Institution. He studied at the University of Berlin 1904-1905. He died on January 23, 1938 in Newton Centre, Massachusetts.
    Scope and Contents
    The papers document the professional work of Anderson. The bulk of the collection consists of newspaper clippings arranged by Anderson. With the exception of 2 notebooks on Luke and Romans and a student grade book, the remaining items relate to Anderson's work at Second Baptist Church in Rochester, NY.
    - Newspapers clippings arranged alphabetically by subject assigned by Anderson, including on Academic and missionary education, Baptist polity and principles, Liquor and politics, Socialism, etc. (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
    - Notebook related to gospel of Luke (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Notebook related to Romans / Grammatical notes (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Letters to Anderson related to Second Baptist Church, Rochester, New York, 1889-1890, no date (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Documents related to case of Stephen Robinson and "Jennie" and Second Baptist Church, Rochester (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Second Baptist Church, Rochester, Sunday School membership lists and lessons (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
  - Andros, Thomas
    Thomas Andros was born May 1, 1759, in Norwich, Connecticut. He joined the revolutionary army at the age of 16 and fought in the battles of Long Island and White Plains. He enlisted on a privateer in New London in 1781, but was captured and kept on a prison ship in New York. A few months later he escaped and began studying theology in Plainfield, Connecticut, with clergyman Joel Benedict. He was ordained in Berkley, Massachusetts, in 1788 and remained at the First Congregational Church there for 46 years. He died in Berkley on December 30, 1845.
    - Two manuscript sermons, on the texts Malachi 1:6 (1794) and Luke 24:26 (1796), 1794, 1796 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Anthony, Alfred Williams
    Anthony (1869-1939) was born in Providence, RI and graduated from Brown University (1883) and Cobb Divinity School (1885). He was ordained to the Free Baptist ministry in 1885 and pastored the Essex Street Church in Bangor, Maine from 1885 to 1888. He was professor of New Testament Exegesis at Cobb Divinity School from 1890-1908 and professor of Christian Literature and Ethics at Bates College 1908-1911. Thereafter he served in various adminstrative positions for the Free Baptist and American Baptist churches.
    - Letters of Anthony, primarily addressed to his seminary classmates as a group, 1891-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
    - "Alfred Williams Anthony - a Sketch by his daughter", No date (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bailey, Albert Edward
    Bailey (1871-1951) was an authority on art and religion. He taught classics, religious education, and English at the Worchester Academy (1891-1910), was head master of the Allen English and Classical School, West Newton, Massachusetts (1900-07),and thereafter traveled and lectured. He was an instructor in religious pedagogy at the Newton Theological Institution and Andover Theological Seminary.
    - Typescript writings by Bailey, including "Education as the Contact and Communion of Minds", "Protestant Glass Houses", "Three Kinds of Minds", No date (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Contents of notebook related to Survey of Art course taught at Central YMCA College, Chicago, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Contents of notebook related to Survey of Art course taught at Central YMCA College, Chicago, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
    - Course outline for workshop survey of Western art taught at Hiram College, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Materials related to Bailey's course "Art as a Teaching Instrument" at Andover Newton, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Barrows, Homer
    Barrows was born in Wareham, MA in 1806. He graduates from Amherst College in 1821 and received a certificate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1834. Ordained as a Congregational minister in 1836, he served churches in Lakeville, MA (1836-1842, 1869-1872), Norton, MA (1842-1845), Dover, NH (1845-1852), Wareham, MA (1852-1859), and Plaistow, NH (1859-1869). He died in Andover, MA in 1881.
    - Diaries: 6 volumes (1842-1843), (1843-1844), (1844-1846), (1869-1870), (1870-1873), (1873-1877), 1842-1877 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Correspondence: including from C. Washburn to HB, from HB to Middleboro and Taunton Precinct, to HB from churches in Norton, North Andover, and Wareham; from HB to First Congregational Church, Wareham, 1834-1852 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript sermons written by Barrows, 1834-1872 (Box 4, Folder 8-12)
    - Miscellaneous papers, including notes, poem, attendance statistics kept by HB for North Haverhill and Plaistow, receipt for funeral expenses of HB, 1859-1880 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Church-related records, including minutes of ecclesiastical councils related to employment of Barrows, from Dover, NH and Wareham, MA, 1842-1859 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified correspondence - connection to Barrows not clear, 1840-1904 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bartlett, Ernest Merrill
    Bartlett was born in Warner, NH in 1870. He graduated from Amherst College in 1894 and attended Union Theological Seminary, NY 1894-1896. He received a B.D. from Andover Theological Seminary in 1897 and was ordained as a Congregational minister. He served the Rockdale Church in Northbridge, MA (1897-1900), the church in Kingston, MA (1900-1904), and Pilgrim Church, Madison, WI (1904-1905). He died in Madison, WI in 1905.
    - Undated sermons arranged by title, including "Certain Easter messages", "Jesus Christ and Social Problems", "Liquor Legislation - a failure", "Why should anyone be naked or hungry", No date (Box 5)
    - Undated sermons arranged by text: Genesis - 1 Corinthians, No date (Box 5)
    - Undated sermons arranged by text: 2 Corinthians - 1 Peter (Box 6)
    - Dated sermons, 1895, 1897 (Box 6)
      An index to Biblical texts of the dated sermons is available in Box 5 with the original inventory of the collection.
    - Dated sermons, 1898 January - 1899 April (Box 7)
    - Dated sermons, 1899 May - 1900 (Box 8)
    - Dated sermons, 1901-1902 (Box 9)
  - Berkeley, James Percival
    Berkeley was born in Salt Lake City, UT on January 21, 1879. He graduated from Marietta College, OH in 1905 and received a B.D. from Newton Theological Institution in 1908. He was ordained at First Baptist Church, Bellingham, MA on September 29, 1908. From 1909 to 1950 he taught at Newton Theological Institution in the fields of Religious Education and Bible, with breaks for study at the University of Glasgow (1914-1915) and Union Theological Seminary, New York (1919). Berkeley died September 19, 1971 in Newton, MA
    - General correspondence, 1945-1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letters to son James L. Berkeley, 1952-1957 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Sermons, lectures, syllabi related to Gospel of John, 1945-1951 (Box 10, Folder 3-29)
    - Sermons and notes related to the Psalms, 1941-1966 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
    - Miscellaneous notes and notebooks (Box 12, Folder 1-23)
    - Bound syllabi for Old Testament course (2 volumes), 1955 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Typescript writings, including on Mark and Acts, No date (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Bible, Bible portions - annotated by Berkeley (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Personal items and memorabilia (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, drawing: portraits of Berkeley (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Photographs: miscellaneous, including family (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Bigelow, Asahel
    Bigelow (1797-1877) was born in Boylston, MA. After attending Phillips Academy, he graduated from Harvard in 1823 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1826. He served churches in Walpole, MA (1828-1849) and Hancock, NH (1850-1877).
    - Manuscript sermons, arranged chronologically, 1833 April - 1863 January (Box 20)
    - Manuscript sermons, arranged chronologically, 1864 February - 1875 January (Box 21)
  - Boardman, George Dana
    George Dana Boardman (1828-1903) was born in Burma, the son of the Baptist missionaries George Dana Boardman and Sarah Hall Boardman. He graduated from Brown University in 1852 and from the Newton Theological Institution in 1855. He was pastor of the Second Baptist Church in Rochester, New York from 1856 to 1964 and pastor of the First Baptist Church, Philadelphia, from 1864 to 1894. Boardman was a founding member of the Brotherhood of the Kingdom in 1892, and was active in the Social Gospel movement.
    - Bound volume containing three editions of Boardman's work The Problem of Jesus, reviews of the book, and letters received by Boardman from various individuals, thanking him for the gift of the book., 1891-1897 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Boynton, Grace Morrison
    Grace Boynton was born in 1890, the daughter of Nehemiah Boynton and Mary Ella Wilcox. After graduation from Wellesley College in 1912, Boynton taught English literature at Yenching University in Beijing, China for more than two decades. She died in 1970. Additional materials regarding Boynton work in China are available in Record Group 11, Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia. A more complete collection of personal papers is housed at Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe College, Harvard University.
    - Correspondence: letter from Boynton to Aunt (1921); letter from S. Parkes Cadman to Boynton family following death of Nehemiah Boynton, 1921, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Lecture notes, writings, photographs related to Chinese gardens, including for "Harvard lectures on Peking gardens", 1941, no date (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
    - Notes for lecture on "Etiquette Bandits and Warlords", 1959 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Typescript writing: "The Garden Perils of Sylvester Shilling" (106 pages), No date (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Typescript writing: "Heart's Desire" in various drafts, with letters to/from potential publishers, 1951-1952 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Typescript writings: "The Man About the House" and "Two on the Tide", No date (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes and writings, 1947, no date (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Publicity file and memorabilia, 1937-1962 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
    - Photographs: personal and family (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Photographs: primarily from time in China, 1922-1952 (Box 16, Folder 12-13)
  - Boynton, Nehemiah
    Nehemiah Boynton was born November 21, 1856 in Medford, Ma. He graduated from Phillips Academy, Andover, and Amherst College. Following his graduation from Andover Theological Seminary in 1882 he was ordained and served as a Congregational clergyman in Littleton (1882-1884), North Church, Haverhill (1884-1888), Union Church, Boston (1888-1896), First Church, Detroit (1896-1906), and Clinton Avenue Church, Brooklyn (1906-1920). He served as a trustee of Andover Theological Seminary 1907-1916, including as president of the Board 1914-1916. Boynton died November 8, 1933 in Medford, MA.
    - Correspondence, 1888-1926 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
      Correspondents include: James M. Gordon, George A. Hood, George M. Boynton, Lucius C. Porter, Luella Miner, Frederick W. Stevens, Chauncey Goodrich. See full listing in first folder.
    - Sermons preached at Union Church (listing of titles, texts) (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1888 May - 1889 April (Box 17, Folder 4-23)
    - Sermons arranged chronologically, 1889 September - 1891 March (Box 18, Folder 1-14)
    - "The Log of a Sea Dog" - unpublished writing by Boynton in manuscript and typescript formats, with some clippings included, 1907-1919 (Box 18, Folder 15-29)
    - "The Sky Pilot Afloat" - unpublished writing by Boynton in typescript, No date (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Notes and photograph from World Alliance conference, 1922 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1882-1922 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Personal items and memorabilia (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Photographs (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Charles Rufus
    Brown (1849–1914) was an American Baptist clergyman and Biblical scholar. He was born in Kingston, New Hampshire, graduated from the United States Naval Academy. Following his resignation from the U.S. Navy in 1875 he he studied at Harvard, Newton Theological Institution, Union Theological Seminary, and the universities of Berlin and Leipzig. In 1883 he became associate professor of biblical interpretation and in 1886 professor of Hebrew and cognate languages at Newton Theological Institution.
    - Correspondence, 1888-1913, no date (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Sermons, 1883-1907 (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
    - Published writings, 1906, no date (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Typescript lecture notes (Box 22, Folder 5-7)
    - Handwritten notes (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Examination questions for courses taught at Newton Theological Institution (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Collected material (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Calkins, Wolcott
    Calkins was born on June 10, 1831 in Corning, NY. He graduated from Yale College in 1856 and taught at schools in New Haven, CT and Worcester, MA from 1856 to 1859. He attended Union Theological Seminary, NY from 1859-1860 and the University of Halle, Germany from 1860 to 1862. He was ordained as a Congregational minister in 1862 and served the following churches: First Congregational, Hartford, CT (1862-1864), Calvary Presbyterian, Philadelphia, PA (1864-1866), North Presbyterian, Buffalo, NY (1866-1880), Eliot Congregational, Newton, MA (1880-1895), Montvale Congregational, Woburn, MA (1898-1907). He died in Newton, MA on December 31, 1924.
    - Handwritten exegetical notes and writings on the Gospel of Mark (1 volume); "Romans in Plain English - a paraphrase of Paul's Epistle to the Romans" (4 volumes) (Box 23)
    - Unpublished manuscript: "The Divine Farewell - A verbal exposition of Johns' Gospel Chapters 14-17", 1st edition (1 volume), 1868-1883 (Box 24)
    - Unpublished manuscript: "The Divine Farewell - A verbal exposition of Johns' Gospel Chapters 14-17", 2nd edition (10 volumes) (Box 24–27)
    - Handwritten exegetical notes and writings on the Epistle to the Galatians (1 volume), 1868 (Box 27)
  - Carpenter, Chapin Howard
    Born on June 29, 1835 in Milford, NH, Carpenter graduated from Harvard College (1859) and Newton Theological Institution(1862). He was ordained in 1862 and appointed by the American Baptist Missionary Union for service in Burma (now Myanmar). He served at the Rangoon mission until 1868 and then at the Basein mission until his return to the United States in 1880 due to ill health, except for one year as President of Rangoon Baptist College (1874-1875). Carpenter published writings on the subject of self-supporting missions. He resigned from the American Baptist Missionary Union in 1886 and travelled to Nemura, Japan to establish an independent mission. He died there on February 2, 1887.
    See original finding aid available at repository for more detailed listing of address and paper titles and sermon texts.
    - Brief autobiographical account of Carpenter's religious experience, 1862 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Detailed daily journal describing Carpenter's work in Burma, 1862-1878 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Two handwritten poems; letter from Kate Brown to John Smith, 1854, 1855 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Undated addresses, including " Charge to the Siamese Karen Missionaries", "Christian Missions in Burma", "The Work of Female Missionaries in the Foreign Field", No date (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Addresses, including on perseverance, "Christian Work in British Burmah", for Vermont Baptist Convention, 1851-1873 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Addresses, including before the Social Union, Boston, and at memorial service for Rev. A. T. Goodell, "The Mission of England", 1874-1885 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Undated sermons arranged by text, No date (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Dated sermons, arranged chronologically, 1860-1867 (Box 28, Folder 8-12)
    - Dated sermons, arranged chronologically, 1868-1881 (Box 29, Folder 1-5)
    - Undated student papers, No date (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Papers from time at Leland Academy, 1852-1854 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Papers from time at Harvard College, 1856-1859 (Box 29, Folder 8-11)
    - Papers from time at Newton Theological Institution, 1860-1862 (Box 29, Folder 12-15)
    - Lecture notes from Newton Theological Institution, arranged alphabetically by professor: Hackett, Hovey, Train, 1860-1862 (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
    - Papers related to Carpenter's work in Burma, including "Brief Account of Bassein Karen Mission", "Karen Villages in the Me Klong (Redstone) Valley", 1864-1878, no date (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Articles by and about Carpenter (2 bound volumes) - including reactions to and reviews his work Self-Support - illustrated in the History of the Bassein Karen Mission", 1862-1884 (Box 30, Folder 6-7)
    - Clippings: articles responding to and reviews of Self-Support and an article by Carpenter, 1880-1885 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Articles about Alvah Hovey and other Baptist ministers - scrapbooks compiled by Carpenter (2 bound volumes) (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Cochrane, Wilbur Willis
    Born in Monmouth, ME on April 16, 1858, Cochrane graduated from Colby College (1885) and Rochester Theological Seminary (1890). He served as a Baptist missionary in Hsipaw, Shan State, Burma (now Myanmar). He was a member of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland and author of The Shans published in Burma in 1915.
    - Correspondence from Taw Sein Ko of Office of Government Archaeologist, Mandalay regarding Cochrane's research on Shan history and language, 1906 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with W. Clifton Dodd regarding Shan language, 1908 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence from Taw Sein Ko, Government House, Rangoon and Charles O. Blagden of London regarding Shan language, 1910 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Taw Sein Ko, Office of Examiner in Chinese, Burma, regarding Shan and Burmese history, literature, language (18 letters from Taw;1 letter from Cochrane), 1914 January - March (Box 32, Folder 4-5)
    - Letter from American Baptist Foreign Mission Society regarding donation of Cochrane materials to Andover Newton Library, with lists of manuscript titles, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 6)